<!-- __COPYRIGHT__ -->
<cvar name="ESCAPE">
<summary>
A function that will be called to escape shell special characters in
command lines. The function should take one argument: the command line
string to escape; and should return the escaped command line.
</summary>
</cvar>

<cvar name="LIBPREFIX">
<summary>
The prefix used for (static) library file names.
A default value is set for each platform
(posix, win32, os2, etc.),
but the value is overridden by individual tools
(ar, mslib, sgiar, sunar, tlib, etc.)
to reflect the names of the libraries they create.
</summary>
</cvar>

<cvar name="LIBPREFIXES">
<summary>
An array of legal prefixes for library file names.
</summary>
</cvar>

<cvar name="LIBSUFFIX">
<summary>
The suffix used for (static) library file names.
A default value is set for each platform
(posix, win32, os2, etc.),
but the value is overridden by individual tools
(ar, mslib, sgiar, sunar, tlib, etc.)
to reflect the names of the libraries they create.
</summary>
</cvar>

<cvar name="LIBSUFFIXES">
<summary>
An array of legal suffixes for library file names.
</summary>
</cvar>

<cvar name="OBJPREFIX">
<summary>
The prefix used for (static) object file names.
</summary>
</cvar>

<cvar name="OBJSUFFIX">
<summary>
The suffix used for (static) object file names.
</summary>
</cvar>

<cvar name="PLATFORM">
<summary>
The name of the platform used to create the Environment.  If no platform is
specified when the Environment is created,
&scons;
autodetects the platform.

<example>
env = Environment(tools = [])
if env['PLATFORM'] == 'cygwin':
    Tool('mingw')(env)
else:
    Tool('msvc')(env)
</example>
</summary>
</cvar>

<cvar name="PROGPREFIX">
<summary>
The prefix used for executable file names.
</summary>
</cvar>

<cvar name="PROGSUFFIX">
<summary>
The suffix used for executable file names.
</summary>
</cvar>

<cvar name="SHELL">
<summary>
A string naming the shell program that will be passed to the 
&cv-SPAWN;
function. 
See the 
&cv-SPAWN;
construction variable for more information.
</summary>
</cvar>

<cvar name="SHLIBPREFIX">
<summary>
The prefix used for shared library file names.
</summary>
</cvar>

<cvar name="SHLIBSUFFIX">
<summary>
The suffix used for shared library file names.
</summary>
</cvar>

<cvar name="SHOBJPREFIX">
<summary>
The prefix used for shared object file names.
</summary>
</cvar>

<cvar name="SHOBJSUFFIX">
<summary>
The suffix used for shared object file names.
</summary>
</cvar>

<cvar name="TEMPFILEPREFIX">
<summary>
The prefix for a temporary file used
to execute lines longer than $MAXLINELENGTH.
The default is '@'.
This may be set for toolchains that use other values,
such as '-@' for the diab compiler
or '-via' for ARM toolchain.
</summary>
</cvar>
